hi I'm Bret contus this is the fourth
video in a four-part series that I
filmed uh to just lend support to an
article I wrote that was published on
strengthcoach.com I figured there' be a
lot of questions and a lot of times it's
easier to to explain things um through a
video than in writing so uh I'm just
going to roll through a bunch of
different concepts so first of all in
sports there are six main load vectors
um there's the axial load Vector which
is up in down this is like jumping okay
that's axial there's the acceleration
vector which is a mixture between axial
and anop posterior and the acceleration
vector is when you're leaning or when
you're jumping forward that's the
acceleration vector the third Vector is
the anop posterior Vector this is when
you're sprinting full speed you're
upright and you're sprinting at full
speed this is anop plus here front to
back the fourth Vector is the cutting
vector cutting side to side it's also
called the medialateral vector all right
this is when I Juke from side to side so
that's that's the fourth one the fifth
load Vector is back pedaling this way
that's postero anterior or back the back
pedaling vector and then the sixth one
is the twisting Vector the torsional
vector that's when you twist you know
when you when you're swinging or when
you're throwing and that's characterized
by hip external rotation
and then you need strong obliques as
well so those are the six load vectors
so if you want to be Sports specific you
need to train all six of those load
vectors well I'm going to roll through
some different concepts but um we'll get
back to this load Vector concept okay
first myth I want to expose is the
hyperextension myth people think
hyperextension is bad well
hyperextension of the low back is bad
it's unsafe but hyperextension of the
hip is perfectly safe in fact we can
hyperextend in the hip 20° with straight
legs 10° with bent legs and then 30°
while being forced back and that's
perfectly natural we do it every time we
walk run Sprint if you thrust someone
off you when you're grappling um when
you do a lunge or a Bulgarian Squat and
even when you do a a hip flexor stretch
you're hyperextending so hyper extension
of the hip is good because that's where
the glute Maximus gets to exert its
strongest effect
the best exercises for the glutes are
hip hyp extension exercises okay next
myth glut Max and glut medius uh myth
people think the gluteus maximus does
this the gluteus medius does this and
that's not true uh I measured the glute
activation the glute medius the upper
glute and the lower glute and very
interesting the best exercise for the
gluteus medius were actually bent leg
hip hyperextension exercises the best
exercises for for the upper gluteus
maximus in half the individuals I tested
were abduction exercises and then the
best exercise for the lower glutes were
always bent leg hip hyp extension
exercises so the lower glutes just do
hip extension hip hyper extension the
upper glutes they do hip extension hip
hyp extension they do hip abduction
transverse abduction and external
rotation so the upper glutes are like
the most versatile muscle in sports okay
next myth the sprinting and jumping myth
all right people think a lot of strength
coaches think the best exercises for
jumping are also the best exercise for
sprinting and that's not true I tested
the muscle activation of sprinting and
jumping and sprinting activated like 200
I can't remember 230% more glute than
jumping did so sprinting is a lot more
hip extensor dominant whereas jumping is
a lot more quad dominant so you can't
just do you know exercis that mimic
jumping and expect it to make your
athletes faster if you want your
athletes to jump higher give them
exercise that look like jumping so that
squat deadlifts you know static lunges
these all look like jumping if you want
to get an athlete faster give them
exercises that look like sprinting we
can't be standing when we do that though
just like bench press we don't normally
take cables and push this way we lay
down on a bench to get more stability to
maximally activate our PCS same thing
with the glutes and the hamstrings we
have to do them there's there's
basically three different ways there's
exercise that pull the the the leg
rearward with straight legs exercise the
and then pull the legs rearward with
bent legs and then exercise the push the
hips forward which can be straight leg
or bentle as well and exercises that
push the tors so rearward which could be
straight leg or bent leg so uh the
exercise where the legs are straight
they're the best hamstring exercises the
exercis where the legs are bent those
are the best glued exercises so we have
to do you know prone or supine or
quadruped movements to mimic the
sprinting Vector which brings me my my
next point for some reason in in sport
specific training we think since sports
are played on the on you know on two
feet while standing you have to do all
your exercise well standing well
standing is great it teaches you you
know coordination and balance and and
the standing exercise like squats deados
and lunges are best for the jumping
Vector but if we want to train the
sprinting and the acceleration vectors A
lot of times we got to get on the ground
or lay across something so that the the
whole sport specific thing where do all
your exercise on two feet if you stick
to that the most you're going to get
your your athlete glute activation up to
is about 55% in the deadlift whereas the
exercise of it I that that I do well
even sometimes people can do a body
weight quadruped hip extension or a body
weight single leg glute Ridge or even a
body weight reverse hyper get more glute
activation from a body weight exercise
than from a one R Max squatter Dev it's
crazy muscle activation is specific to
the directional load Vector so if you
want to get better at sprinting you have
to do in this Vector anop posterior or
the acceleration vector which is a
mixture okay um this kind of goes along
with what we we've been saying but the
best glute exercise I could go on Google
and type in a search for best butt
exercise or best glute exercise and I
could probably print you out 300
different articles that said squats dead
lless lunges these people have never
actually measured the muscular activity
of glutes they're just going by what
they think or what they've been told I
measured the muscular activity over a
100 different exercises including every
squat lunge deadlift you know back
extension reverse hypers straight legs
bent legs machines
apparatuses bands dumbbells barbells uh
you know everything I could and I
learned what the best exercises were and
I tested four different people it's in
my book Advanced Techniques and Glu
maximi uh strengthening which you can
find on my website www.the glut guy.com
so if you want to learn about muscle
activation buy that book and read it
you'll be smarter than 99% of trainers
and coaches with what exercises work
which muscles so the one's for the
glutes for the lower glutes it's always
a hip hyperextension which means front
to back so like a a bent legged glute
bridge where you're pushing forward or a
pendulum quadraped hip extension where
you're uh pushing back this way it's
always something front to back anop poer
loaded and it's hip hyp extension the
best exercise for the upper glutes are
either is some people it'll be a hip
bent leg hip hyper exension exercise in
some people it will be an abduction
exercise so that's why you got to do it
all you train all the load vectors and
you'll lead to a well-rounded routine a
balanced
routine okay um the last thing I want to
say is some coaches are way ahead of
their time in the 1980s Charlie Francis
was given his athletes uh reverse leg
presses he'd have them St facing away
from a of a leg press on a universal gym
and they would push rearward that was a
really good exercise back then he was
years ahead of his time the exercise I
showed you are even better than that so
watch the first three videos think about
the load Vector concept and it'll just
make you a better Coach and make your
athletes better thank you